<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great law of nature, or, Self-preservation examined, asserted and vindicated from Mr. Hobbes his abuses in a small discourse, part moral, part political and part religious.</title>
            <author>Shafte, J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21245</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12296337</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12296337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59037</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59037)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 193:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great law of nature, or, Self-preservation examined, asserted and vindicated from Mr. Hobbes his abuses in a small discourse, part moral, part political and part religious.</title>
                  <author>Shafte, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 89, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and are to be sold by Will. Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to J. Shafte. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1]-[7] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hobbes, Thomas, 1588-1679.</term>
               <term>Natural law --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT LAW OF NATURE, OR SELF-PRESERVATION, Examined, Aſſerted, and Vindicated from Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Abuſes.</p>
            <p>In a ſmall DISCOURSE; Part <hi>Moral,</hi> part <hi>Political,</hi> and part <hi>Religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Will. Crook</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis ſmall Treatiſe was writ two or three years ago, and ſince hath remain'd in the hands of ſome friends, till now at laſt I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured it to cenſure. It is chiefly the reſult of a few ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts upon conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſome of <hi>M. Hobbes</hi> his ſtrange Tenents, which he would ſeem to ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Great Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:59037:3"/>Self-preſervation; whereby, in the judgment of the world, he takes away all Foundations of Virtue and Goodneſs: yet is he well approved of by many, who would be thought like him, Great Wits, and to have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings and Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties much tranſcending the Doctrine and Pedantry of Moraliſts and Divines.</p>
            <p>Knowing therefore with whom I have to do, I have argued chiefly out of Maſter <hi>Hobbes</hi> his own Principles, and thereby endeavoured to evince the groſneſs and folly of his Errours, in making
<pb facs="tcp:59037:3"/>all Juſtice, Honeſty, Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Goodneſs and Vertue, the conſequences only of a Civil Government; as if, where there were no Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, theſe things had no being; and where there is a Civil Magiſtrate, took their meaſures only from his Mouth: So that whatſoever he pleaſes to call Good, Juſt, Honeſt, Vertuous, muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only neceſſarily be ſo; and whatſoever he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Evil, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Diſhoneſt and Vicious, immediately, for the ſame reaſon, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo to all his Subjects; And theſe Enormous Tenents
<pb facs="tcp:59037:4"/>he pretends to deduce and ground upon his Definition of the Right of Nature, and the Great Law of Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. This ſhameful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe both of God, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and all that dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any thing of real goodneſs and vertue, I have endeavoured to detect and confute out of his own grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Principles: which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I have effected, I muſt leave to thy judgment: And doubt not, but Truth and Reaſon will prevail at lengh with the Intelligent and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional: And that they may ſo do with all, I have linked
<pb facs="tcp:59037:4"/>them alſo with Interest; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured thereby, to leave none that love themſelves unconcerned in the matter of the ſubſequent Diſcourſe, and out of the reach of the arguments and reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, according to the best of my understanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. l. 19. for <hi>non,</hi> read man; page 86. l. 20, 21. blot out this whole ſentence, <hi>viz.</hi> if others will interpoſe, let it be at their perils.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59037:5"/>
            <head>THE Great Law of NATURE, OR SELF PRESERVATION, EXAMINED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Notions or Laws of Right and Wrong, Juſt and Unjuſt, Good and Evil, are independent upon, and naturally and rationally antecedent to the Conſtitution of any Commonwealth, or Civil Government, and are binding or obligatory to all men, both in the ſtate of Nature, and in all Political Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; proved out of Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his own Principles of <hi>Self-Preſervation,</hi> and equality amongſt men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the Nature of God; with a ſubſequent Diſcourſe, ſhowing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of that Tyrannical and Arbitrary Government, ſeeming to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59037:6"/>vindicated, and held neceſſary by the ſame Author in his ſaid Book: with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother light reflection upon the Juſtice and Reaſonableneſs, or rather the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Unreaſonableneſs of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who in any Civil Government will challenge to themſelves Liberty of Conſcience, or a publick free exerciſe of what Religion they beſt fancy; being all grounded upon the ſame Principles of <hi>Self-preſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the greateſt part of theſe fore-mentioned Errours ſeem to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his definition of the Right of Nature, I will firſt begin with that.</p>
            <p>By the way requiring one thing only to be granted, <hi>viz.</hi> That Right Reaſon is to be the Law and Rule of all our actions. By Right Reaſon, I do not mean as Mr. <hi>Hobbes, De Cive,</hi> pag. 21. every mans private Reaſon; for who but himſelf did ever call this Right Reaſon? but I mean what is commonly hereby meant, an unerring Reaſon, or that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds always upon true Principles, and thence deduces true Conſequences and Concluſions.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59037:6"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Definition of the Right of Nature Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</head>
               <p>THe Right of Nature, which Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters commonly call <hi>Jus Naturale,</hi> is the liberty each man hath to uſe his own power, as he will himſelf, for the preſervation of his own Nature, that is to ſay, of his own Life, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of doing any thing which in his own judgment and reaſon he ſhall conceive to be the apteſt means thereto: In his <hi>Leviathan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though we ſhould freely aſſent to the firſt part of this definition or deſcription of the Right of Nature, which we do not, yet may we be well allowed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the inference or conſequence thence deduced: For though it ſhould be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Right of Nature is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty each man hath to uſe his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as he will himſelf for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Nature, yet is the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59037:7"/>guilty of a moſt notorious Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is therefore a liberty that each man hath of doing any thing which in his own judgment and reaſon he ſhall conceive to be the apteſt means thereto; for in his own judgment and reaſon, he may, and often doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the apteſt means thereto, which <hi>re vera</hi> is not, but rather quite contrary to it, and the apteſt and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt means to bring him to deſtruction; of which infinite examples might be produced, and every mans daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence confirms this for a moſt undeniable truth.</p>
               <p>And what rational man will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that becauſe he hath a right and liberty granted him by God or Nature, to preſerve his own life, or another mans, will conclude, that hereby is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to him a Grant of a Right and Liberty to deſtroy himſelf, or another?</p>
               <p>Now according to the definition it ſelf, the Right of Nature is only a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that each man hath to uſe his power for his own preſervation, not his own deſtruction; for this ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to infringe the Law of Nature and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59037:7"/>Reaſon, to the breach of which no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man will ever pretend to any Right, which commands Self-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and this is meant, I ſuppoſe, of a real preſervation, not a ſeeming or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentional only; therefore the means, in order to this end, ought to be really and truly, and not only ſeemingly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally (in the party acting) condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the end; otherwiſe the Law of Nature will <hi>re vera,</hi> really and truly be broken, contrary to deſigne and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: for ſeeing that this is the great Law of Nature and Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-preſervation; to act that which is really and truly contrary to this Law, muſt needs be a breach thereof, though the man ſo acting may be ſo far in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as not to think the action to be ſo deſtructive to the end he aims at as it is: And therefore I affirm, that though a mans own judgment and reaſon prompt him to do a thing as ſeeming to him the apteſt means to ſecure this end of Self-preſervation, which thing really and truly is not according to the rule of right reaſon the apteſt and moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means to attain this end aforeſaid,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59037:8"/>this man is guilty of miſuſing that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty given him, guilty of tranſgreſſing the rule of right reaſon, which obliges all men, at all times, in all places; and guilty of acting that which is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary and prejudicial to his own preſervation, the end and deſigne of his actions: nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> excuſable, becauſe he did that which to himſelf ſeemed moſt conducing to the end; for as in Civil Government, ignorance of the Law is no good Plea to excuſe and juſtifie, though it may ſomewhat extenuate a Crime in ſome caſes; ſo in <hi>ſtatu-naturae,</hi> errour, ignorance or paſſion, cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and juſtifie thoſe actions which are really contrary to right reaſon, or that principle of Self-preſervation. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each man deſires to juſtifie his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by right reaſon, and chiefly of all other things, deſires, intends and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours Self-preſervation; each man here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by implies, and doth acknowledge, that every act contrary to right reaſon, &amp; this Principle of Self-preſervation, is folly, which he condemns; though if you come to urge him with a particular caſe of his own, ignorance, partiality and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59037:8"/>pride, (becauſe he would ſeem no leſs wiſe then he ought to be) may make him indeavour to juſtifie his own acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with a gloſs of reaſon, though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and in themſelves, irrational, and deſtructive to the end he aims at. Now becauſe no man is abſolute Maſter of right reaſon, it follows, that all men are guilty of tranſgreſſing the Laws thereof, amongſt which Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Chief; and this frail condition of man is agreeable to the Leſſons taught by the Divine Law-givers, <hi>viz.</hi> That man is born in ſin, and under an ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable neceſſity of ſinning, as he is in the ſtate of Nature; becauſe he is not always able to regulate all his actions according to the exact Rules of right reaſon.</p>
               <p>It is be objected, That if we grant Self-preſervation a conſtant Rule and Maxime of right reaſon, a man in <hi>ſtatu naturae</hi> not knowing but every one he meets may have an intent to kill him, ought, according to the rule of this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to prevent the dauger if he can, by killing the other firſt, or reducing him into a condition not to be able to do him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59037:9"/>any prejudice, and this act ſhall be good and juſt, becauſe rational, and ſo by conſequence all other inferiour acts of hoſtility; therefore no active and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive juſtice and injuſtice, good and evil, in <hi>ſtatu naturae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That if ſuch act or acts be really and truly moſt conducing to the end of Self-preſervation, we will <hi>diſputandi gratia</hi> ſuppoſe them good and juſt, or not evil or injuſt. And to try this, let us examine them according to the Principles of Equality and Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation agreed to by the <hi>Hobbiſts:</hi> As firſt, That Nature hath made men equal in power; if therefore you go about to take away the Life of any man, there is as much reaſon and probability to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he may take away yours, as you his; and ſo if you attempt to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him any other thing that he hath right to: Therefore whenſoever you attempt any ſuch act, conſider, that by reaſon of the equality that is betwixt you naturally, you do, as it were, upon even terms, throw Dice for your Life. But this is not all: ſuppoſe you conquer and kill, yet doth there reſt as many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59037:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch Battels to be fought by you, as your ſhall finde men in the World, for the ſame reaſon which bids you ſuſpect one, and fight him, bids you ſuſpect all; ſo that you are to throw Dice (as it were) for your Life, not once, but a hundred, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand times: And were it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Madneſs, then Reaſon, to ſuppoſe that you ſhall win every throw? And if you imagine your ſelf to have a little more craft in the Game you are to play then another, ſo as by cunning, skill, ſtrength, confederacy, deceit, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you may conceive more hopes of prevailing then another, you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the Principle of Equality already allowed; the ſame hopes, for the ſame reaſons, and all the ſame advantages, being common to others, and your ſelf lying as obnoxious to them, as they to you; and you may expect to meet with as cunning Gameſters as your ſelf, and to be caught upon the ſame odds, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizals and diſadvantages. By this it appears, that even in the ſtate of Nature, ſuch attempts to take away the Life or the right of another man, are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right reaſon, and regulated
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59037:10"/>by the well-weighed rules of Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: But to kill, <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> all Laws adjudge juſt and allowable. To ſum up in ſhort what I have ſaid, I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That
<list>
                     <item>For a man to do that which is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to his own Life and happineſs, is againſt the Right and Law of Nature and Reaſon:</item>
                     <item>But for a man to do any thing, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, which in his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reaſon he ſhall conceive to be the apteſt means for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his own Life, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is to do that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to his own Life and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: <hi>Ergo</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>For a man to do any thing, or every thing, which in his own judgment and reaſon he ſhall conceive to be the apteſt means for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Life, is oft-times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Right and Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon, and no man can have any Right by Nature to act contrary to theſe Laws.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The major needs no proof; the minor is proved by all men, as often as by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59037:10"/>their own folly they bring miſchief and deſtruction upon themſelves, which when it is too late they commonly ſee, confeſs and condemn. Now though there be a neceſſity of acting according to each mans private reaſon, right or wrong, and conſequently of acting not ſeldom contrary to the principles of right reaſon and ſelf-preſervation, yet is every ſuch act a failing or ſin, and all men in ſome degrees guilty thereof: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom they are moſt excuſable, who indeavour moſt to finde out the true rules of right reaſon, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe rules to regulate their own private actings; they moſt culpable, who not attending to that more Noble principle, ſuffer themſelves to be led by the bruitiſh part of non-ſenſe and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only.</p>
               <p>To give more light to what hath been ſaid, and to examine more exactly the nature of right and wrong, good and evil, according to the granted princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of equality and ſelf-preſervation, let us conſider the firſt of theſe according to Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Aſſumption, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. of his <hi>Leviathan,</hi> in theſe words,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59037:11"/>viz. <hi>Nature hath made all men equal in the Faculties of the body and minde, as that though there be found one man ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times manifeſtly ſtronger in body, or of quicker minde then another, yet when all is reckoned up together, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man is not ſo conſiderable, as that one can thereupon claim to himſelf any benefit to which another may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as well as he.</hi> See <hi>Chartes</hi> in the beginning, <hi>De Methodo,</hi> to this purpoſe, as to the faculties of the minde, which only makes the man.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore that all men are by Nature equal in power, and that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the power of each man, we ſhall meaſure his right and title to what he lays claim to (as he is in the ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) which is adequate and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to his power (according to Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Principles) the power of all men being equal by Nature, their right and title to all things they lay claim to muſt be alſo equal, and if their right and title be equal, then ought their ſhare and parts to be equal in the ſaid things; Nature in giving them equal power, declaring that they have equal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59037:11"/>right, and ought to have equal porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof: Therefore though we agree with Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> that every man in the ſtat of Nature hath right to every thing; yet do we not agree, that this right extends to the whole thing if there be Competitors, but to a juſt and equal portion of it.</p>
               <p>And from this Fundamental Theſis of Equality in Power amongſt men in the ſtate of Nature, before the Conſtitution of any Commonwealth, the rules men are to live by, in this ſtate of Nature, may rationally be deduced: As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in thoſe rules which are that part of the Moral Vertues which reſpect our Neighbours.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Seeing men are equal by Nature, one man ought not to take to himſelf a greater liberty in his actions, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or concern another man, then he is willing another man ſhould in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which reſpect or concern him; for this would be an impugning the natural equality betwixt them, in abridging the power of his Fellow, and inlarging his own; and conſequently the other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of reaſon may, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59037:12"/>therefore it ought to be expected he will by force maintain and defend his own juſt rights. Hence the Rule of Juſtice and Equity, <hi>Do not to others, what you would not they ſhould do to you:</hi> From which it is evident;
<list>
                     <item>1. That no man ought to take that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty over the perſon of another, as to affront, abuſe, impriſon, hurt or kill him, becauſe he is not willing another ſhould take the ſame liberty over him; and this branch of Juſtice concerns the perſon, and perſonal injuries.</item>
                     <item>2. One man ought not to endeavour to abridge another of that right he hath to all things equally with himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not willing he himſelf ſhould be abridged in the ſame by another: And this is the ſecond branch of Juſtice, which concerns the right and injoyment of things appertaining to the perſon of each man.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Seeing men are equal by Nature, in the ſtate of Nature, one man ought not to expect any greater ſervice, as due to himſelf from another, then he thinks due from himſelf to another; for that were to abridge another mans liberty, in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59037:12"/>making him more a ſervant then his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, contrary to the equality betwixt them, and therefore, according to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he ought to expect that the other will maintain and defend his juſt rights by force. Therefore ſeeing it is evident others are not obliged to do more for you, then you are obliged to do for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>do unto others as you would they ſhould do unto you;</hi> Hence it follows, that we ought to think our ſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do all good Offices for others up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every juſt occaſion, becauſe we deſire and think the ſame due to our ſelves from others; and this is called Charity; and theſe two Vertues of Juſtice and Charity, are the grounds, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and the very ligaments of all Humane Society; and all Covenants, or Pacts, expreſs or implicite, whereby Commonwealths are conſtituted, or one man obliges himſelf to another, are binding as acts of natural Juſtice, which one man ought to obſerve towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the rules of reaſon, grounded upon Equality and Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; it being contrary to the rules of Juſtice for a man to infringe his faith
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59037:13"/>and promiſe given to another, whereas he himſelf would not another ſhould do ſo to him: And upon theſe two Laws of Juſtice and Charity, all other Moral Vertues, which reſpect our Neighbours, are grounded; and actions are eſteemed vertuous or vicious, good or evil, as they are conformable or repugnant to theſe two Laws: As for example, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerate ſome particulars; Gratitude is a point of Juſtice in returning kindneſſes received; for as you would expect that others ſhould pay obligations of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to you upon occaſion, ſo ought you to do to others: So ſincerity in all your dealings and tranſactions with others is a point of Juſtice, becauſe you deſire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould deal ſincerely with you: So to keep promiſe or Covenant; ſo of Mercy, where you have had juſt provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and ſuffered injuries, Charity bids you pardon, becauſe you deſire to be pardoned: All other Vertues, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting our Neighbours, are eaſily reduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſame Heads. Contrary to theſe Laws, and injurious to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, are Pride; to arrogate to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more then is due, and to put too
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59037:13"/>high a value upon himſelf, and too low upon another, this is injuſtice: So of all kinde of wrong, as Theft, Murder, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, Affronts, Back-biting, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, Lying, Malice, Envy, Hatred, Cheating, Diſſembling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to ſuffer theſe things from another, therefore in Natural Juſtice he ought not to do them to another.</p>
               <p>Now there is another ſort of Vertue and Vice which hath no reſpect to our Neighbours, or not ſo much to them as to our ſelves; and the meaſure of theſe, with their reaſons and grounds, may be deduced only from the Law of Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: Such is Temperance in all things that concern our ſelves, as in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drinking, recreation, ſtudy, exerciſe either of the minde or body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which actions are ſo far allowable, as they are conſiſtent with Self-preſervation, that is, the health of our bodies and mindes; and if we exceed in them ſo far as to prejudice our health, we deſtroy our ſelves, and ſin againſt Nature, or the Law of Self-preſervation.</p>
               <p>And as we have demonſtrated that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Charity and Temperance, with all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59037:14"/>their ſubordinate Species, do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reſult from the conſideration of theſe two Maximes of Equality and Self-preſervation, without any reference or dependancie upon a Civil Power of Commonwealth; ſo alſo doth it appear of the notions of good and evil, which in a Moral ſenſe are nothing elſe but Vertue and Vice; ſo that ſo long as men are men, <hi>viz.</hi> rational beings, and are acted and governed by reaſon, they muſt all neceſſarily agree in theſe Notions of good and evil; every vertuous action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing denominated good, every vicious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction evil. And hereby it appears, that theſe are not things meerly arbitrary, or dependant upon the mouth of the Prince, or the Conſtitution of a Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it being impoſſible that any Civil Power ſhould make thoſe actions, which in themſelves are good, that is, condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the general happineſs of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, as Juſtice, Charity and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to be evil; or thoſe things which are evil, as Injuſtice, Uncharitableneſs. Intemperance, to be good, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deſtructive to that happineſs; Therefore theſe are not things depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59037:14"/>upon the Conſtitution of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or the mouth of the Civil Magiſtrate; but the Conſtitutions of all Civil Governments and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths are depending upon them, and if not framed according to them, muſt needs be ruinous and pernicious to as many as live under ſuch Governments, or the greateſt part of them; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Natural Juſtice, Charity and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, it is in vain to think any Civil Government can ſubſiſt, the deſigne of all Civil Government being the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Laws, in order to Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; there being no need of any Civil Magiſtrate, if theſe Laws could be made to be obſerved without their help; nor doth any benefit accrew to any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their Magiſtrate and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where theſe Laws and Rules are not obſerved; and to exempt the Prince from the obſervation of them, is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt the people, who are to obey him, and to reduce all things into a <hi>Chaos;</hi> for theſe being the Laws of Reaſon and Self-preſervation, the non-obſervance of them is to act contrary to both, and the conſequence deſtruction.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59037:15"/>
               <p>And that theſe Laws, even in <hi>ſtatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Naturae,</hi> do oblige in <hi>foro conſcientiae, viz.</hi> to a deſire that they ſhould take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> accords: If then the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oblige to a deſire, whereſoever the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Self-preſervation, and the actual exert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that deſire may conſiſt together they certainly oblige to actual perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; for whoſoever is obliged to a deſire that he might do a thing, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly obliged to do it, where he may do it with ſafety, eſpecially where with benefit and advantage to himſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Now that the actual performance of theſe Laws of Nature are always conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with Self-preſervation, is evident from what I have before ſhewn, <hi>viz.</hi> that they oblige only to do that, which according to the rules of right reaſon, is moſt conducing to that end, the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al performance whereof muſt needs be always requiſite; and therefore to ſay they oblige only in <hi>foro interno,</hi> or to a deſire, is as much as to ſay a man is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged always to deſire Self-preſervation, but muſt not uſe the means to ſecure it.</p>
               <p>And as for that Objection, That the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59037:15"/>practiſe of Juſtice and Charity, in a ſtate of Nature, is not the means to preſerve our ſelves, becauſe it would expoſe good men as a prey to the danger, luſts and paſſions of evil men, who would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no ſuch Laws in their dealing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us:</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That it is neither againſt the Law of Nature, nor Reaſon, or every man to ſtand upon his guard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be as cautious as he can, and as jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as he pleaſes, or ſees cauſe, of thoſe with whom the hath to deal, unleſs he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> well acquainted with their diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and temper: and it is very lawful for him to put himſelf in a condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd and preſerve his own right, but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o doing, he muſt not prejudice ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for that were to provoke and pull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe dangers upon himſelf, againſt which he deſires to ſecure himſelf; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Rule of Juſtice, <hi>Do not to others what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u would not others ſhould do to you,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls every man in the ſtate of Nature, as hath been ſhewn) that he is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure another: And the ſame Rule tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that whoſoever dath to us an injury, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at perſon thereby declares, that he is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59037:16"/>willing to be looked upon as an Enemy, and muſt in reaſon and Juſtice expect a like return of hoſtility: for he who doth injuries, ought in Juſtice and Equity to expect the ſame, and cannot complain of injuſtice, if the party injured take from him the power of doing him any further injuries, even by taking away his life, if in reaſon it appear he cannot otherwiſe ſecure his own: But where more gentle proceedings are likely to take place, there the rigorous are always to be avoided, becauſe more dangerous to our ſelves, and deſtructive to others: So that though by the rigour of Juſtice you may requite one injury with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet according to the Rule of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, you are to ſuffer injuries, and do good for evil, and forgive your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe you deſire when you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend others in the like manner to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably dealt with, and forgiven your ſelf: beſides, it is more ſafe to ſpare an Enemy, then proſecute him with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rigours, leſt either he himſelf ſhould in a deſperate condition make as deſperate a reſiſtance, or ſome others ſeeing your cruelty towards him, ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59037:16"/>ſerve you the ſame ſauce, as with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is to be expected. You ſee therefore theſe Laws of Nature, Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, do not binde up our hands, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to the abuſes and injuries of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but gives us liberty to uſe the means, according to right reaſon, moſt likely to ſecure us: But if we will fooliſhly conceit, we cannot be ſafe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ſubdue all we ſee, and make them our Vaſſals; or will upon every ſlight injury, or weak ſurmize of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended injury, do a real one, this is not according to the rule of right reaſon, moſt conducing to our preſervation, but will certainly and ſuddenly, at ſome time or other, be our deſtruction: Much leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an it be juſt and reaſonable, where there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s no cauſe of fear nor danger from a man, to abuſe, rob, ſpoil, wound, hurt or kill him.</p>
               <p>Now though it be certain, that if men would live according to the Laws of Nature, I do not mean that Nature which is common to man with Bruits, but that which ſpecifically conſtitutes mans Nature, and diſtinguiſhes him from other inferiour Creatures, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59037:17"/>Right Reaſon, (for every one hath but ſo much of Man in him as he hath of Reaſon) they might live happily and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, as in the Golden Age celebrated in the Fictions of the Poets of Old: yet becauſe men are acted very much by the inferiour principles of appetite and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, common alſo to the Beaſts, which are always ſtrong and vigorous in them, and becauſe no man is abſolute Maſter of Right Reaſon, nor are all men in equal degree Maſters thereof; hence it is, that generally they are ſwayed by paſſion, blinded by ignorance, byaſſed by ſelf-love, pride and conceit, or intereſt; which imperfections each man eaſily perceives, and takes notice of in others, but ſeldom can, or will ſee, or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in himſelf: So that though every man in the ſtate of Nature ſhould agree for quietneſs and ſecurities ſake, that each ſhould have an equal ſhare or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in all things, and equal ſervices done as required of him, yet when theſe agreements come to be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, they would not agree in their accounts and calculations of the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual and juſt meaſure to be aſſigned to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59037:17"/>each in particular; whence Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Strife and War ariſe. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void thoſe miſchiefs, and that each may enjoy what in Juſtice and Equity belongs to him without ſtrife or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Reaſon adviſes them, as the only remedy, that they ſhould chuſe one or more to adminiſter Juſtice, and to ſit as ſole Arbitrator of all Cauſes, and that they ſhould unanimouſly agree to ſubmit themſelves to his or their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and determination in all their concerns, who is by mutual Covenant to ſee Juſtice impartially executed. But becauſe ſuch Judge or Judges ſo conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted cannot execute their charge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Power able to force obedience in the diſobedient and refractory; it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo neceſſary that all agree to give to ſuch Judge or Judges, ſuch Power as is neceſſary to bring Offenders to juſt puniſhment, and defend the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth from violence; and this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is thus transferred to the Supreme Authority choſen, <hi>viz.</hi> by Promiſe, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant or Oath, expreſs or implicit, to aſſiſt him or them with the hazard or life and eſtate, to the utmoſt of each
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59037:18"/>mans power, in all things neceſſary for the executing Juſtice, and defence of the Commonwealth; of which neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Supreme Power to be Judge, and not the Suject: And this Supreme Power is not only to be Judge of what is juſt betwixt one of his Subjects and another, but alſo of what is juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt himſelf, and any of them, or all of them together; yet are not all his actions therefore juſt, nor any of them juſt, any further then they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable and conſentaneous to the Law of Nature or Reaſon, whereby he is obliged to aſſume to himſelf no greater liberty of Command over his Subjects Perſons and Eſtates, then is neceſſary for the accompliſhing thoſe ends for which he is conſtituted their Prince, <hi>viz.</hi> execution of Juſtice, and defence of the Commonwealth; and if he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume any greater, he is abſolutely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, unleſs that liberty be granted to him by the general conſent of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for though the people transfer to their Soveraign ſo much of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and right as is neceſſary to execute Juſtice, yet this Authorizing him to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59037:18"/>Judge, and obliging themſelves to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to his Decrees, doth not make thoſe Decrees of his to be all juſt; for then were it impoſſible, in this ſenſe, for any Judge or Arbitrator to do an act of injuſtice; which is contrary to what hath been already proved: and therefore we conclude, that when any Prince or Power in Authority Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, acts contrary to the Laws of Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he doth wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and unreaſonably, in regard ſuch actions tend to the deſtruction both of himſelf and people, though for any ſuch acts done, he is not: accountable to any Earthly Power; for if you give his Subjects Authority to call him to account for his actions, you muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Commonwealth diſſolved in ſo doing, the Miniſter of Juſtice being diſabled to execute his duty, becauſe under check and reſtraint, and in the power of others. And thus far we have argued only upon thoſe principles which Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> makes uſe of, and which are before the conſtitution of a Commonwealth, both <hi>natura,</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, viz.</hi> equality amongſt men, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59037:19"/>ſelf-preſervation. And this I have done, and ſhall do, not becauſe it is my own opinion that there are no other grounds or foundations of good and evil, but this Principle of Self-preſervation and Equality; but to ſhew out of theſe Principles granted by Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> that thoſe Eternal Laws of Juſtice, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Temperance, Reward, Vertue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he by the ſame Principles ſeems to deſtroy, or make the Daughters on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Civil Government, are the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and the Foundation of it, and grounded in the very nature of man, ſo as to oblige him to act according to them, though there were no Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in the world, or though the Magiſtrate poſitively command the contrary.</p>
               <p>Now Reaſon will dictate to us ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Principle, from whence, and the ſame Rules of Equality and Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation already laid down, the ſame things may be deduced and confirmed more ſtrongly and effectually, <hi>viz.</hi> that Juſtice and Injuſtice, Right and Wrong, Good and Evil, are not conſequents on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a Civil Government, ſo as to leave
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59037:19"/>no place for any Evaſions to any man that will acknowledge that he ought to govern himſelf by the rules of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and this principle is, That there is a God; which may be proved, and is evident: 1. From the order of cauſes in the world, it being to every mans indifferent judgment, that hath any, apparent and clear, that there muſt be a firſt cauſe. 2. From the order and method of the Univerſe it ſelf, and the admirable frame of it, and the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therein; which ſhews that they were not the effects of Chance, but of ſome wiſe and skilful Architect. 3. From the general conſent of all men in all Nations, and of the wiſeſt men, and greateſt Maſters of Reaſon, that have been in the world: and that which the moſt part of all, and the moſt part of the wiſeſt agree to, at leaſt is moſt probably true. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Reaſon tell us we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is a God, the firſt Cauſe, Creator, and Architect of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; the ſame Reaſon will alſo tell us, that whatſoever perfection we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in our ſelves, or in the Univerſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59037:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>beſides, we muſt conclude to be in the Creator and Giver in a far higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree then in our ſelves, or the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for nothing can give to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what it hath not in it ſelf: Let us therefore conſider what things we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the greateſt perfections and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. Now above all others, we ſet the higheſt value upon Power; therefore in the firſt place we call God Omnipotent, and attribute to him all Power; and becauſe Power without goodneſs may be idle or hurtful, as we finde by experience, in the ſecond place we denominate him Good; which we ſee verified, in that he hath made uſe of his Power in creating us, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us whatſoever we have, that we can call good: and alſo becauſe Power without Knowledge or Wiſdom, may erre in its Operations; therfore, in the third place, we denominate God Wiſe, or Omniſcient; and in theſe three At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, or Perfections, are contained all others; for he that hath Power, and is thereby able to do all things, and Wiſdom, and thereby knows what is beſt to be done, and how beſt to do
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59037:20"/>it, being alſo Good, we are not to doubt, but that we are to expect from him all things that are the reſults of Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating. Hence therefore you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that he is Eternal, True and Juſt; the Oppoſites of which, <hi>viz.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Falſe and Unjuſt, are all contrary to the Attributes of Omnipotent, Good and Omniſcient. It being thus demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, that every man, according to the Rule of Right Reaſon, muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is a God; and that this being ſuppoſed, we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily believe, that he is owner of all Perfections; and that thoſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes afore-mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, Omniſciency, and Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the greateſt perfections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his; and we being all by the right of Creation and Dominion his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, we ought, according to the rule of reaſon, to believe that he will do Juſtice to every one according to his Nature, and the Office of a Soveraign; and therefore we ought to be careful to live according to the Laws of Juſtice already by reaſon determined, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59037:21"/>command us, <hi>not to do to others what we would that others ſhould not do to us, and to do to others as we would that others ſhould do to us:</hi> For though we ſhould, in acting contrary, fooliſhly hope to eſcape the ill conſequences that we ought reaſonably to expect we ſhall hereby draw upon our ſelves from the hands of men; yet ſeeing there is no hope left to eſcape an Omnipotent and Omniſcient Judge, the Rule of Self-love, or Self-preſervation will command us, not to do thoſe things, which if not moſt certainly, yet certainly moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably will bring evil and deſtruction upon us, from the hands either of God or men: And this is argument ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to determine the judgment and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of all men that reſigne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Government of Reaſon; and to thoſe only I ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Now if any take notice that I have given a notion of God according to the notions that men have of perfection, whereas I ſhould have given a notion of perfection according to the true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Attributes of God; it being fitter to ſay, Whatſoever is in God is a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59037:21"/>perfection abſolute and univerſal, then to ſay, Whatſoever is amongſt men a perfection, is a ſhadow or Character of God: I anſwer, ſeeing we can frame no other notion of God any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then by attributing to him what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we eſteem, according to reaſon, moſt excellent and perfect; Hereby it appears, that it is the good pleaſure of God that we ſhould really believe him to be ſuch as we have ſpoken him to be, it being moſt reaſonable, we ſhould think it his pleaſure we ſhould judge of all things, and therefore of him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe faculties he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us to judge by: which we have done. And ſeeing it is the will of God we ſhould really believe him to be ſuch as our faculties declare to us, we ought alſo to believe, that he really in his own Nature and Eſſence is ſuch, becauſe the ſame faculties reaſonably judge, that he is no deceiver, for that is an Attribute inconſiſtent with the former perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that conſtitute his Nature.</p>
               <p>And thus I have demonſtrated, that every man ought to believe there is a God, that this God is good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59037:22"/>juſt, ſeeing Juſtice (as we have ſhewn before) is good, and a good ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, and moſt conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the good eſtate of the Univerſe; and therefore the preſumption of him that does evil, and yet hopes to eſcape the hands of men, though it does, for the moſt part, bring him at one time or other to deſtruction, even by the hands of men, and is therefore unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; yet the conſideration of a God being alſo in the way, ſuch preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be the greateſt madneſs, and abſolutely contrary to the Rules of Self-preſervation, the Principles whereupon we have proceeded.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing we have proceeded thus far upon theſe Principles of Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and the Equality amongſt men by Nature, as to deduce from thence the Laws men are to live by, and the Nature of Good and Evil, as to the Conceptions which man muſt neceſſarily, in reſpect of himſelf, frame thereof; and thereby made it appear, that Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> abuſes and perverts his own Principles, in order to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall Diſecurſe; we will declare
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59037:22"/>more at large, not what Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> underſtands, but what in reaſon ought to be underſtood and meant by the word <hi>Self-preſervation,</hi> leſt any ſhould conceive I intend no more thereby, then barely the preſerving of life, or a <hi>bene eſſe</hi> in this life, which would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the notion I think we ought to have of it, by a great miſtake; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Opinion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Self-preſervation, when he makes it the great Law of Nature, it is manifeſt to any indifferent judgment, that hereby ought to be intended, not only the preſervation of life, or a <hi>bene eſſe</hi> in this life, but a general deſire that neceſſarily and naturally is in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rational creature, whereby they wiſh to themſelves happineſs and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which may properly be called <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lautia,</hi> or ſelf-love, or is grounded thereupon, and is infinite as deſire, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning parallel with Eternity it ſelf: for every man doth not only naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to preſerve his life, or to live hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in this world, but to be for ever and eternally happy, freed from grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous objects, and conjoyned to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59037:23"/>and deſirable; and this I think un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable: and hence it appears, that this <hi>Philautia</hi> is the Center upon which every mans actions move, and finally are determined and directed; it being impoſſible for any one indued with a rational ſoul, rationally and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to deſire to be miſerable, or not to deſire to he happy. This therefore being acknowledged for the great and neceſſary Law of Nature, it muſt of neceſſity be granted, as a conſequence plainly deducible from hence, that that is always to be accounted beſt and moſt Eligible by each man, that conduces moſt to that particular mans real hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; and that moſt of all to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of by the Univerſal ſuffrage and conſent of all men joyntly, that is moſt conducing to the benefit, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and ſatisfaction of all men: and it is eaſily viſible upon the obſervation of the whole frame of the Univerſe, and the nature of man in particular, that if we ſubmit to the judgment and dictates of right reaſon, each mans private happineſs will be found linked together with, knit and united to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59037:23"/>happineſs and felicity of the reſt of his Fellows, as to this life; the greateſt pleaſures whereof are found to conſiſt in Society, and the benefits we have by the mutual commerce, company and injoyment of one another: And this is the reaſon that people deſire to unite themſelves in Commonwealths, and under Civil or Politick Governments; and a more powerful and effective rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I think, then that of fear, which Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> ſeems only to inſiſt upon, though I acknowledge them both to be ſtrong motives. Now ſeeing that a Civil Government, for the reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged in our former drſcourſe, and this laſt mentioned, is neceſſary, as much conducing to the better and more comfortable eſtate of mankinde in this life, the Diſpute will ariſe, what kinde of Government is to be deſired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, the common Species talked of. I ſay, that Government is moſt to be deſired, which is moſt conducing to the end for which it is deſired, which, as hath been ſaid, is the ſafety and more pleaſant comfortable living of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59037:24"/>all the men in the world, and this, I think, no man can plauſibly cavil at: Conſider then which of theſe diſſerent Species of Government, laſt mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, do moſt conduce to this propoſed end, <hi>viz.</hi> the general ſafety and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable living of all mankinde, and not only of this or that particular perſon, or ſome ſort of men; and I am much miſtaken if any man will deliberately, propoſing this end of Government, adjudge Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Monarchical Tyranny to be ſuch; that is, for all men to ſubmit their Lives, Eſtates, and all their Concerns, only to the will and pleaſure of one Man, and he to be Sole Proprietor and lawful diſpoſer of them all, without doing wrong or prejudice to any; nay, as it ſeems by his Principles, without poſſibility of doing any injuſtice, injury or evil: Such an abſolute power in any one mans hand, is too great and unſafe, unleſs we could ſuppoſe him always the beſt of men, or little leſs then ſome Divinity. But ſuppoſe he be, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Fool or Mad-man, or get ſome diſtemper in his brain, either by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59037:24"/>or any other accident, how ſhall ſuch a one manage the Sword of Juſtice with an equal hand? his will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be the ſame with <hi>Caligula</hi>'s, that all the people of his Juriſdiction had but one Head, that he might cut them all off at one blow, or the like fumes of madneſs, melancholy or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy: And certainly no man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the uſe of reaſon, whilſt he ſees and knows himſelf, and all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns in this life, ſubject to the will, humour, and extravagancy of ſuch a one, can think he lives happily or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, though he yet ſee the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dark ſtorm fall beſides himſelf. If it be urged, that if we do make a King, it is not poſſible to make him with a limited power, becauſe if there be any other power in being that can check and controul him, that power is ſaperiour to him, and therefore he but a ſubject to this: I anſwer, That he may have a power limited by the Rules of Natural Juſtice and Fquity, which oblige all men, Kings and others, not to do wrong; and limited alſo by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and National Laws, or expreſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59037:25"/>Covenants, to which he may be obliged by Oath, Promiſe or Covenant; and ſuch a limitation I only mean, which is a ſufficient Obligation and reſtraint to a good and juſt, or any reaſonable and wiſe Prince.</p>
               <p>In an Ariſtocratical Government, though there be not ſo much danger that all the Rulers may agree together to deſtroy or abuſe their Subjects, yet doth ſelf-ends and intereſt carry them very often upon projects and private deſignes, and beget Factions, dangerous and of fatal conſequence to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
               <p>A Democratical Government is moſt difficult to be continued, ſome, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all caution and care of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, growing more eminent and powerful then the reſt; and ſpurred by ambition, attempting the ſubverſion or diſturbance of the Government, and often, at laſt, grow too powerful for the Commonwealth, and change the face of the Democratical into a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Government, as in the Roman Commonwealth did <hi>Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To avoid the inconveniencies of each
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59037:25"/>ſeveral Species, it is evident, that the well compounded Government, as that of <hi>England,</hi> is the beſt, under which it is moſt manifeſt that the people live the moſt happily, I mean all ſorts and degrees, the Commons as well as the Lords, of any Nation in the world; where though there be one Monarch, and the Government reſembling that applauded by Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> yet doth he not pretend to that abſolute arbitrary and unlimited power Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> would give his Prince; the Laws and Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative Power being not ſolely poſited in him, without the concurrence and conſent of the People by their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives, though the Execution of them only be in the King, with other Royalties and Prerogatives, whereby he is ſufficiently inabled to do Juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Subjects, and defend them againſt the ſtrongeſt of his and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. And though if you reſpect ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power abſtract from Juſtice, it is in the Kings to pervert theſe Laws e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, at leaſt as to the execution of them; yet with Juſtice he cannot do it, nor without imminent danger
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59037:26"/>to himſelf and his people: for though Subjects ought not to take upon them to oppoſe and reſiſt their Princes acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether juſt or injuſt, as hath beer ſaid, otherwiſe then by Petition, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to be the Miniſters of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Commands; and ſuch Doctrine they ought to be well inſtructed in, with the reaſons thereof; yet is it very difficult to impoſe this belief upon men, for each man naturally thinks himſelf concern'd, as a Subject, to a higher Prince then any upon earth, <hi>viz.</hi> the God and Creator of all things, to maintain and uphold the Eternal Laws of that King of Kings; ſo that where a Prince, the greateſt in the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doth an act of apparent wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, or which is ſo conſtrued and apprehended, all parties ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and apprehending it, do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by conceive the Majeſty of that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt King offended; and conſequently, conſidering alſo the caſe to be of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral concernment, and may be their own, they deſire and wiſh to ſee ſuch irregularities (as they conceive them) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormed, and thereupon often ingage in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59037:26"/>the quarrel unadviſedly and precipitate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as being both Gods, and their own private, and that of all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, wherein to die a Martyr muſt meeds be Meritorious; not conſidering, that the thing which they conceive to be unjuſt, may not withſtanding be moſt juſt and reaſonable, and the errour not in their Prince, but in their own private Opinion and Judgment; and not conſidering, that if the Prince did pervert Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar acts wherein he did ſo, would not be of ſo bad a conſequence to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, as the remedy they did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, <hi>viz.</hi> a Civil War: which if ſo, then are they themſelves guilty of a greater injuſtice, in bringing greater calamities upon a Nation, to avoid the leſſer; and what greater calamity can be then ſuch a War?</p>
               <p>Now the Conſtitution of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England</hi> is ſuch, that beſides the old Laws, approved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages of experience, no new Laws binde the people, which are not, or have not been ratified by their own conſent: The King therefore that is to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59037:27"/>Rule according to thoſe Laws, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> certainly be more cautious in obſerving that they be put in execution, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he were left at liberty, and unconfined<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and his own Imperial Commands or E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts were only and ſingly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Law; the diverſity betwixt ſuch a Government as this of ours, and ſuch a Tyrannical Government a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> ſpeaks of, being this: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ours, the people can ſay, We have agreed and ſubmitted to ſuch and ſuch Laws and no other, and by theſe we deſire to be ruled, and if you govern or handl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us otherwiſe, you do us apparent wrong, and let God and your own Conſcience judge betwixt us and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whether you obſerve, as you are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the mutual Covenants and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements betwixt us and you: But in theſe abſolute Monarchical Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, there is no ſuch mutual compacts or agreements betwixt the Soveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the People, no poſitive Laws but the Princes Command or Edict; and the people agreeing, or having agreed to be ſubject to ſuch a kinde of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, have no other will then that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59037:27"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f their Prince; it being the ſame a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if hey had ſaid, <hi>We ſubmit our wills to our will, and our ſelves to be wholly overned according to your diſcretion; do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us what to you ſeems good, we and all we have are yours, and you may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe of us and ours as you think fit and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nvenient; your only Edicts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands ſhall be the abſolute Laws to which we willingly ſubmit our ſelves, and which ſhall be by us inviolable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the nature of Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Monarchical Tyranny: Now let any national man judge, whether the Prince, whoſe power, as to the juſt meaſure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and how far it ought lawfully to be extended, is known and determined, and cannot without notorious injuſtice and breach of Covenant be inlarged, will not be more cantious in uſing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me according to moderation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and containing himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Sphere and extent of Juſtice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quity, then he who may, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Laws of the Kingdom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and without ſeeming wrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r injuſtice to his people, by reaſon of their conſent to his Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59037:28"/>do what ſeems moſt agreeable with his own fancies, however extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant and deſtructive to his people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the firſt caſe, the ſenſe of the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent injuſtice opens his eyes to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuch actions, and reſtrains his irregular deſignes; in the latter, no fault is committed the people by the Laws of the Land can juſtly complain of, or the Prince by any Law but Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or natural Equity and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, know to be a fault; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I confeſs, no ſuch pretence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection or diſobedience to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor ſenſe of injury to them done in the Prince: But it is moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, that with all bad Princes, the fear of bringing miſchief upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their wronged, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by provoked, and at laſt inraged peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is a great ſafety, and the beſt Shield of the people to protect and ſecure them from violence and injuſtice. And when the Prince is by expreſs Laws, by Oath and Covenant with his people, poſitively bound to the obſervation of their eſtabliſhed known Laws, which without the general conſent of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59037:28"/>are unalterable: Surely matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus reduced to a certainty, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he method and Laws of Government and Juſtice, the people will, even in the Princes own judgment, much ſooner apprehend and diſguſt irregular and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>njuſt proceedings, having a conſtant Standard to meaſure them by, then when all is referred only to the Princes will and pleaſure; where <hi>quod libet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et, quod licet aequum eſt;</hi> and the Prince, though he vie with all the Records of Hiſtory for all forts of Tyranny and Oppreſſion, yet muſt be thought to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o evil, or at leaſt no wrong to his poor Subjects; and this apprehenſion, and doubt of the bad conſequences which will probably inſue upon ſuch Tyrannical actions, is a great check to Tyranny. And though the Doctrine be admitted moſt certainly true, that for no reaſon whatſoever any Subject ought to take up Arms or wage War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince, no not to preſerve his own life, (which yet Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of) yet will this give no ſecurity at all to the Tyrannical Governour; for but ſew men in the world buſie their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59037:29"/>brains to ſearch out and apprehend the true reaſons of things, as they ought, or are capable of ſo doing; and fewer will be content to ſit ſtill and ſuffer wrongfully (as they conceive) where there is good hopes of defending and vindicating themſelves from wrong, let the wrong-doer be what he will. The number of thoſe that will be diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the juſt and lawful proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a juſt Prince, doth often over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power their Fellows, who are good and loyal-hearted Subjects, as woful experience doth often teach: how much more ought it to be expected, that when the Prince doth, contrary to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the eſtabliſhed Laws, abuſe and Tyrannize over his Subjects, the number of the prudent Loyal, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of peace, ſhould be much inferiour to the number of Male-contents and Mutineers? And hence the danger ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſo often overtakes the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny even of lawful Princes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and the fear that the Prince muſt neceſſarily ſtand in of falling by the number of his irritated and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Subjects, who conceive themſelves
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59037:29"/>wronged by him, will always put ſome reſtraint upon his extravagancy and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, let him be never ſo wicked, if he have but ſuch an indifferent meaſure of prudence or conſideration, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect his own ſafety and eſtate; ſo that the peoples ſenſe of wrong, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten conduce much to the ſecuring them from much oppreſſion under wicked Princes, as it doth often alſo bring great iniſeries and aſſlictions upon them under both good and bad Princes. To reſtrain which natural propenſity that all men have of revenging themſelves, even upon their Princes and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, though with the hazard of a whole Nation, where it lies in their power, for an injury done, or concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be done to them or theirs, though by their Prince; it is very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and neceſſary that the Laws ſhould be ſo ſevere as they are againſt Rebels and diſturbers of the Peace; and yet for all this, all to little to curb the exuberancy of this diſeaſe: for though good effects may ſometimes be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of unlawful and irregular actings, yet ſuch actings ought not therefore
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59037:30"/>to be allowed or approved, becauſe ſuch effects are but accidental, and not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally incident to them; beſides, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt not do evil that good may inſue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but it ſeems a ſecret of Gods Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial contrivance, as in many other like caſes, ſo in this, that the ſins of the Prince, as Tyranny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the ſins of his people, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo <hi>vice verſa,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious humour of the people to be puniſhed by the heavy hand of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince, or ſome other Uſmping Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: Therefore, I ſay, where the Law are made and eſtabliſhed, and thing reduced to as great a certainty as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as to what is juſt or unjuſt, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unlawful, both in reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Subject and Prince, and one Subject and another; though the interpretation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Laws, and the execution of them be left ſolely to the Prince; yet is there much more hopes the people may injoy ſome benefit of theſe Laws, then where there are no Laws ſo eſtabliſhed, but all is left to the will and diſcretion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Prince to make new, or revoke old or do what he liſt: for a Prince tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59037:30"/>will pervert theſe Laws, after they are ſo eſtabliſhed, and he ſworn to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of them, What would the ſame Prince do if there were no ſuch Laws at all to ſtand in the way of his will and deſire? certainly be much more Irregular, Tyrannical, and Exorbitant. Suppoſe the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had been all actually Kings of <hi>France,</hi> or of the Turkiſh Empire, to Rule there accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Cuſtom of thoſe Countries, do you think thoſe Countries of <hi>France,</hi> and the Nations under the Dominion of the Turk, ſhould have been uſed by the ſame Kings with no leſs reſpect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the peoples ſatisfaction, and no leſs Liberties, Immunities and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges allowed them, then to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh. Subjects? Or ſuppoſe the French King, or the Turk, were to govern ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws and Conſtitutions of <hi>England,</hi> amongſt a people inured to ſuch a Government, do you think that the people ſhould preſently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go as much ſervitude under them, as the people they now Rule? No certainly; the different Conſtitutions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though under the ſame men,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59037:31"/>would alter the condition of the people that lived under thoſe men and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and the Princes be thereby and by the humour of the people, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred from abuſing them contrary to their Laws, with the ſame licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they would their other Subjects<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hence it is clearly evinced, that good Laws eſtabliſhed, as in <hi>England,</hi> are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> immediate cauſe, under God, of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> happineſs, freedom, wealth and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, the people living under them as in <hi>England,</hi> injoy above thoſe other people and Nations of the world. And though, in other Countries, the Prince may have a more abſolute Dominion and Arbitrary power, of doing or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing whatſoever to him ſeems good, yet to a good Prince this is no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of felicity, his ſatisfaction and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſiſting chiefly in making his people under him live happily, and with the greateſt aſſurance of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt immunities and priviledges they may be capable o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as Subjects; and therefore deſires not to impoſe any thing upon them, but what is in order to this propoſed end: For why is the Prince
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59037:31"/>ſaid to repreſent God, but becauſe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be as God to his people? whoſe greateſt Attribute wherein we injoy him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing goodneſs, the advantage the Prince hath above all others, is, as God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o do good to ſo many people his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and under the influence of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. And certainly to any ſoul that is livine <hi>aure particula,</hi> that carries in it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Image of its Creator, the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>licity in the world is to do good to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and oblige all by benefits and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſies, or at leaſt to deſerve well at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands of every the meaneſt ſubject or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſon: for this is that which God hath done of all his Creatures; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe creatures which deſire to reſemble their Creator, muſt do ſo by one another; and that man, I think, ought always to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook upon it as a ſpecial favour of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a great bleſſing, in whoſe hands God hath been pleaſed to put the means and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pportunities to delight himſelf in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſing God-like exerciſe of diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing happineſs, and contentment, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the benefits of peace, plenty, riches, honours, immunities, rewards, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good things, to his inferiour Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59037:32"/>or Vaſſals; and that man who findes no ſatisfaction in thus acting the part of God towards his fellow-crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or rather whoſe greateſt and chiefeſt ſatisfaction and pleaſure is not herein found to conſiſt (for <hi>omnium ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſime delitiae ſunt obligandi delitiae</hi>) hath no part of God, nor no reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of him: And let him pretend to what other vertues, excellencies or perfections he will, they all loſe their luſtre without this one Noble qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is their end; and he thus deſtitute of this ennobling perfection of the Soul, which is the light thereof, he reſembles no more the light which is God, but darkneſs his contrary.</p>
               <p>But it may be objected againſt what I have ſaid, that the people under thoſe abſolute Monarchs by Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, being their Slaves and Vaſſals, and all they have theirs in Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, freely to diſpoſe of according to their high Prerogatives, the Prince will be more careful, in this caſe, of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his own, then he would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be if the people challenged, and had abſolute propriety in their eſtates,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59037:32"/>goods and poſſeſſions, and a free di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal of themſelves, and all they had, without being liable, or obliged by any Laws or Commands, but thoſe by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves expreſly made or conſented to; for the Prince being as Maſter of the Family, will be more careful of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and all that appertains to it, looking upon all as his own proper goods, then if he were but a Guardian and Overſeer for anothers benefit.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That it were happy for many men, Maſters of Families, both in reſpect of themſelves and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, if they had not power to waſte their ſubſtance, ruine their eſtates, and be a continual affliction and vexation to all thoſe that are neceſſarily dependant upon them, in ſome ſenſe their poor Subjects and Vaſſals: And how many examples have we of this nature? Is it not the moſt common and ordinary thing in the world, to ſee the Son ſcatter what the Father hath ſcraped together; and by his folly and extravagancy, totally deſtroy all the Monuments of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers frugality, wiſdom and induſtry? And how many families every day fall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59037:33"/>to ruine; and from a plentiful eſtate, are reduced to beggery, or a very low and mean condition, by the miſgovern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Pater-familia's?</hi> How few Ancient Families, of many thouſands, have continued their Hereditary Eſtates and Grandeur from the firſt Foundation of this Kingdom, or but from the laſt ſettlement of it under the Norman? And how many times have the beſt of them been ſhaken, and reduced to a low and very weak eſtate, only by the exorbitancy of their own heads? If Kings then were as Maſters of Families, and governed after the ſame manner, as freely and arbitrarily diſpoſing of all the Profits and Revenues of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the labours of the people; what man is ſo blinde, as not to ſee that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms would be things of no firmer foundation, nor longer continuance, at leaſt under one and the ſame form of Government, and Race of Princes, then Families are, or the Eſtates appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe Families continue under, and in the hands of the ſame Lineal Maſters, whereof one in a hundred doth not continue its felicity a hundred
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59037:33"/>years together; but is without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther default or cauſe then that of the Governour, or <hi>Pater Familia's</hi> thereof, reduced to the greateſt extremities, and in ſome reſpect annihilated? Where is then this care that each man hath of his own Proprieties? And certainly Kings being but men as others are, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging from nature no more nor grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abilities either of minde or body, if they might without oppoſition, and with as much facility, diſpoſe of their Kingdoms and people, as a Maſter of a Family of his Eſtate, many of them being guilty of the ſame extravagancies other men are, would make both their own Grandeur, and their peoples For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, ſubject to the ſame incertainties, periods and viciſſitudes, that ordinary Families are; with this diverſity, that a Maſter of a Family having not ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute a power, is not able to do ſo much miſchief. If it be further object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that many of thoſe Tyrannical Kingdoms, as that of the ancient and preſent Perſian Monarchy, the Turkiſh, Indian, and others, are or have been of long continuance: I anſwer, That
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59037:34"/>even theſe, however they ſeem to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Tyrannical, yet <hi>de facto</hi> they are not ſo: For in the firſt place, each of theſe Countries hath its Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed and certain, beſides Cuſtomes, which arbitrarily to alter, is not in the power of any the greateſt Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Secondly, though the Princes may, according to the Cuſtumes of ſome of thoſe Countries, by their high Prerogative, and without infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any poſitive Laws, take away the eſtate or life of any the greateſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject without any legal proceeding, or good cauſe ſhewn, or real guilt (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws here with us) and ſo often do; yet is it not in their power to change the Souls of men, and make them approve and like well of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and wrong. Hence it is, that further then their abſolute power main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by the ſtrength of a Military force will uphold them to exerciſe theſe Tyrannical actions, they neither can nor dare do them; but the awe of the Souldiery, whoſe intereſt ſuch Princes have commonly linked with their own arbitrary Dominion, and whoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59037:34"/>uſually ariſes out of the oppreſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the people; and the cuſtom where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the people have been inured to ſuch ſubjection, makes many ſuch oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and tyrannies to paſs with leſs op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or diſturbance: But then is not this Prince ſo arbitrary in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as is ſuppoſed; for he can do nothing but what ſhall be liked and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by his Army or Souldiery, with whom he muſt always carry fair, oblige, gratifie, and pleaſe them; and even they, further then their own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt doth byaſs and incline them, will never be drawn to countenance and maintain open injuſtice, injury and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; and the Prince is himſelf in the power of theſe, by whoſe power he tyrannizes over his people; and that it is ſo, is often experienced, they caſting him off upon any diſpleaſure concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſetting up who they pleaſe. But by reaſon it hath been uſual with the Subjects of ſuch Princes to be thus tyrannized over, being well acquainted with the irregular proceedings of their Prince, and the power of his Armies, and having no eſtabliſhed Laws but his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59037:35"/>will, nor no pretence of any Law to defend them, or interpoſe againſt ſuch wrongs, but only <hi>extrema neceſſitas,</hi> or <hi>Lex Natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> they are content to bear much, and much more then will thoſe people, who being inured to another manner of Government, and having poſitive eſtabliſhed Laws, do no leſs. impatiently indure the breach or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of thoſe their Countries Laws and priviledges, though but lightly touching their eſtates, perſons or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, then the others do the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt extremities of tyranny and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Hence it is, that in ſuch Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Governments the Prince having inured the people to ſuffer a far greater meaſure of wrong, hardſhip and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then in ſome other places they have been acquainted withal, may with more ſafety, and leſs danger of provoking them, continue the ſame, then another Prince commanding a freer people, and better acquainted with more liberty, and good uſage, may reduce them to ſuffer from him a far lighter meaſure of injuſtice: which if a good Prince, he will never deſire to do nor attempt; if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59037:35"/>a bad, I ſee not why any man ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that he ſhould finde an eaſie and uninterrupted path to help to go more chearfully, and with greater facility, to the execution of his bad deſignes, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and grinding his people, and making their lives unpleaſant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable. Yet if any man could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me, that the people were made only for the Prince, and not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the people, I could perhaps be more eaſily induced to think, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that made the way more plain and open for the more abſolute Dominion of the Prince; and the moſt abſolute ſlavery of the Subject, were to be made a part of our Creed: But this is a Doctrine no well-adviſed man me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks ſhould ever deſire to ſet on foot, nor no wiſe or good Prince would ever make any uſe of, his peoples greateſt aſſurance of a happy eſtate under his Government being his own greateſt glory and content: And though he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf may be good, and therefore need no reſtrictive Laws to limit him his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; yet he knows not what his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors may prove, or how fit or unfit to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59037:36"/>be truſted with ſo great and arbitrary a power; and therefore is well contented to give the people all the ſecurity he can, which may be conſiſtent with his and their ſafety, for injoying themſelves and their eſtates, in the beſt manner that Subjects can be capable of, without deſiring that all ſhould be arbitrary, and depend only upon the will and fancy of him that ſhall ſit in the Roval Seat; which is that which Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> will needs make Eſſential to it: For, ſaith he, in his Book <hi>de Cive, The rules of good and evil, juſt and unjuſt, honeſt and diſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, are Civil Laws; and therefore what the Law-giver commands is to be taken for good, what he forbids for evil.</hi> And again, <hi>Before Empires there was no ſuch thing as juſt or unjuſt; therefore lawful Kings make thoſe things which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand juſt, by commanding of them; and what they forbid, by forbidding of them, they make them injuſt; and a Subject, cannot ſin in obeying his Prince.</hi> If this ſhould be all taken for Goſpel by all the world, as Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> would have it, there needs no more then the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of a bad Prince or two in each
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59037:36"/>ſeveral Nation, to deſtroy the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mankinde from off the earth. What brave ſport would ſome of thoſe Roman Emperours, as <hi>Nero, Caligula, &amp;c.</hi> have made, if all their Subjects would have been ſo exactly obedient to their Commands? Yet in ſome caſes Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> will allow the Subject to deny obedience to his Prince; For, ſaith he ſoon after, <hi>We muſt not obey the Prince, if he command us to diſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>our God, or not to worſhip him; for to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, or not to worſhip him, can be by none underſtood for any manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Nor had any one, before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of a Civil Government, the Right to deny honour due to God, and therefore could not transfer ſuch Right upon the Civil Power.</hi> Well then, Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> grants the Law-giver is not always to be obeyed: When is it then lawful to diſobey? ſaith Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> When he commands us directly to diſhonour God, or not to worſhip him. And why may we not diſhonour God, or not worſhip him? Sure, I think, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, but becauſe it is directly contrary to the light of Reaſon: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59037:37"/>by conſequence, whenſoever the Law-giver commands us any thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly concrary to the light of Reaſon, we are no obliged to obey, according to Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Conceſſion; and ſuch are all Commands contrary to the Laws of Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtice, Charity, Temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as hath been ſhewn. But Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> will ſay, ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands muſt be directly contrary to the Light of Reaſon, and not by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence only. I will not trouble my ſelf with the meaning of this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but affirm, that whatſoever is by a clear conſequence contrary, is directly contrary to reaſon; and even, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> the Subject, in this caſe, is neceſſarily to be Judge himſelf, whether the thing be directly contrary to reaſon or not which is commanded. And whereas Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> ſaith, <hi>That no man before the Conſtitution of a Civil Government had the right to deny honour due to God, and therefore could not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch right upon the Civil Magiſtrate, and therefore may deny obedience:</hi> I have likewiſe already proved, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conſtitution of a Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59037:37"/>theſe Laws of Nature, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Charity and Temperance, were obligatory, and no man had any right to break them, or diſpence with them; and therefore neither, in theſe caſes, could transfer any ſuch right upon the Civil Magiſtrate. But ſure Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> had forgot his definition of the Law of Nature, when he ſaid, <hi>We muſt not obey the Prince, if he command us to diſhonour God:</hi> For a Prince may command ſuch a thing on penalty of life, and then the very Law of Nature gives us a right to ſave our lives, which is with him <hi>Suprema Lex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus ſpoke to the concerns of men, in reſpect of this life, let us look a little, or rather a great way further; that is, to his concerns after this life is ended, to all Eternity; and by the ſame principle, whereby actions relating to our preſent eſtate are guided and directed, by the ſame is that alſo, viz. <hi>Philautia,</hi> ſelf-love or ſelf-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, taken in a more liberal ſenſe; for God himſelf hath made that the great buſineſs of every intelligent rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal being (as hath been before intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59037:38"/>and by his infinite and gracious wiſdom and goodneſs, hath made thoſe actions which moſt conduce to that end of ſelf-preſervation, to be the ſame with what his own Eternal, and alſo late Laws have appointed and directed to be done: So that inſiſting in that path, and cloſely purſuing that end, we ſhall infallibly pleaſe our great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and do thoſe things which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant and agreeable to his will, and his very Nature and Eſſence (as we ought to believe) for ſeeing he is good infinitely, and wiſe infinitely, out of his infinite goodneſs and wiſdom he hath conjoyned our intereſt with our duty; for certainly we could never have thought that goodneſs in God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the notion we neceſſarily frame to our ſelves of goodneſs, which ſhould have made our intereſt inconſiſtent with his will, and where in endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our own felicity we ſhould have croſſed, his Laws: Therefore (as hath been ſaid) we ought to believe, that God out of his wiſdom and goodneſs hath cloſely conjoyned and united our intereſt, happineſs and felicity, to all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59037:38"/>Eternity, with his own glory, his good will and pleaſure, his own Eternal Laws of goodneſs and wiſdom; which then we ſhall be ſure moſt cloſely to purſue and follow, when we moſt cloſely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue our own intereſt, our own real hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and felicity: and this being granted, confirms and eſtabliſhes thoſe fore-mentioned Laws of Juſtice, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without which it is impoſſible for men to live ſecurely or comfortably in this life; without which there can be no Civil Society; and without which the Generation of Mankinde muſt of neceſſity, in ſhort time, be deſtroyed, and periſh from off the earth: Therefore it ought to be concluded by all, that Juſtice, Charity and Temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are things in themſelves abſolutely good, becauſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely requiſite and neceſſary both to our well being, and the very being of all future Generations, and ſo ſtrictly to be obſerved, even according to the Law of Nature: and whatſoever Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Opinion croſſes or impugnes theſe Laws, confutes it ſelf.</p>
               <p>This being proved before, let's conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59037:39"/>what Religion ought to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in a Common wealth: for though Juſtice, Charity and Temperance, and ſome other Vertues, be granted to make a neceſſary part of it; yet may other matters be admitted, no leſs neceſſary, in ſome reſpects, ſo as they be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with theſe: and herein are men at a great loſs, and a mighty ſtir is made in the world, and not without reaſon, for ſeeing Religion is that which reſpects our eternal happineſs and well being, no wiſe man but will think himſelf therein more concern'd, then in all the comforts and conveniencies of this ſhort life; ſo as he will rather chuſe to loſe all thoſe benefits and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, together with life it ſelf, then loſe himſelf eternally.</p>
               <p>Now certainly, that Religion which hath the beſt foundation in Reaſon and Authority to ground it ſelt upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ght by any reaſonable man to be choſen; and that the Chriſtian Religion is ſuch, hath ſufficiently been proved by the Learned Pens and Arguments of many great and wiſe men; and that it is not only conſiſtent with, but ſtrictly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59037:39"/>the obſervation of thoſe great Laws of Juſtice, Charity and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we all know and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: And that the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, are the Books wherein this Religion of ours is fully comprehended and taught, or at leaſt that all that is in them compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended is true and authentick, is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally agreed to by moſt that profeſs Chriſtianity; only the ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Text, the various Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of men, who differ in their Opinions and Judgments, is the great occaſion of that confuſion that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and the great differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religions; all pretending to ground their Tenents upon equal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of Scripture: for where it is agreed on all hands, that the concerns of the life which is to come, are to be preferred before this preſent, as being of infinite greater and larger conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, becauſe relating to our eternal good or bad eſtate; Hence it is moſt clear and evident, that according to the Laws and Rules of Self-love, or Self-preſervation, every man is obliged to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59037:40"/>do thoſe things that may aſſure, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure unto him his future everlaſting happineſs; and for no conſideration, regard, or reſpect of any temporary or tranſitory pain, penalty, pleaſure or profit, to loſe or hazard the loſs of himſelf, as to his future eſtate: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, according to the ſame Laws, he ought only to purſue thoſe ſteps that lead directly towards this end of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eternal happineſs, without treading awry, or erring to the right hand or the left; yet becauſe no man is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but each one ſubject to many fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and errours, in point of judgment as well as otherwiſe, all that can be done, is only for every man to do that which in his own judgment and reaſon he ſhall conceive the apteſt means to this end, praying Gods aſſiſtance, and to him referring the event: and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates and determinations of this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reaſon of his, is that which he calls his Conſcience; which though certainly in many things erronious and miſtaken, yet ſeeing that to him it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears otherwiſe, he muſt needs think himſelf obliged to obſerve and purſue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59037:40"/>the reſolutions thereof; and therefore looking ſtill upon the End, Eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, unto which his Conſcience, as he conceives, directs him the true way, though perhaps in truth very erroniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deceitfully; he is no leſs zealous in proſecuting theſe fallacious paths, pointed out to him by his ill-diſcerning Conſcience, then if they were real'y the true ways. Nor is he to be blamed for doing that which he conceives the apteſt means to the juſtly deſired end he aims at, but for miſconceiving that to be an apt means, which is not: Therefore the beſt remedy to avoid the great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that happen upon ſuch miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and conſcientious errours, is for each man to lay aſide that high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit he hath of himſelf, and to put off his pride and prejudice, and retain but a moderate eſteem of his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as eaſily miſled and abuſed; and to conſider with himſelf, that ſeeing there are ſo many different Opinions concerning one and the ſame thing, both in point of Religion, and other matters; and that all thoſe who differ in Opinion from himſelf, and from one
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59037:41"/>another, are men, and therefore, upon that account, equal to himſelf; and though ſome inferiour, yet other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſuppriour to him in reaſon and knowledge. Hereupon he ought hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with himſelf to conceive, that it is no leſs probable he himſelf may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and his Conſcience miſled and abuſed, then ſome one of his Fellows: For methinks it is high arrogance and preſumption, for any the wiſeſt man upon earth, to ſuppoſe all his own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions infallible truths: And though <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and <hi>diſtincta perceptio,</hi> according to <hi>Des Chartes,</hi> be a great and ſtrong te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for the truth of the thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; yet men will deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a firm belief that they have that clear and diſtinct perception of the truth of a thing, when to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens judgments, and even in truth and reality, they are in a manifeſt and apparent errour, and are after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards themſelves convinced of it; and a firm belief that a thing is ſo as the party doth conceive it, though not grounded upon ſound reaſon, nor upon the evidence of a clear and diſtinct
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59037:41"/>perception, but only upon fancy, enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſms, miſconceit, ignorance or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, is no leſs ſtrong to over-rule and determine the affection, and, even the minde and judgment it ſelf, then the evidence and demonſtration of the moſt infallible truths, grounded upon the cleareſt perception the minde of man is capable of: So that a mans firm belief, and unſhaken confidence of the truth of a thing, though in the higheſt degree i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable, is no ſound argument to prove that he is not in an errour. Let therefore every one conſider his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as no leſs deſirous of that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he is in purſuit of then himſelf, and to have a Soul, with Reaſon, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Conſcience, equal with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. No man will ſcruple to ſay, this Neighbour of his is miſtaken in his judgment, and abuſed with falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Principles of Religion: and in reaſon, why may not you who are ſo cenſorious of another, be as worthy of cenſure your ſelf? eſpecially if you have no better Warrant for your Opinions, then the charitable belief you have ever had of your own, or your own Sects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59037:42"/>to judge of the truth; which in reality are no more nor greater, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps inferiour to that of your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, whom you condemn: So that if you will ſet aſide this over-balance of ſelf-conceit, which only gives you the advantage, in your own Opinion, to any other indifferent Judge, there is perhaps as much, or a greater probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, you are in an errour, then your Neighbour; or elſe that both are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Let every man therefore ſuſpend his zeal, and look to the grounds of his Conſcience, without prejudice, pride, and ſelf-conceit; examine them over and over again, eſpecially let him try them by the Touch-ſtone of theſe three Cardinal Vertues, of Juſtice, Charity, Temperance, and what others right reaſon dictates, and if after all this it will ſpeak no other Language but what it did before, I ſay, then he ought at leaſt in conſcience to proceed in his own ways, though he afterwards may finde, perhaps too late, his Conſcience but a vain Opinion, and ill-grounded ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: for his Conſcience being the ſame with his judgment, it is evident, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59037:42"/>this often failing and abuſing him in many eaſie and familiar matters, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject even to the tryal of his outward ſenſes, or in points of his Calling, wherein with reaſon he may pretend to the greateſt skill; it muſt be great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in him to be ſo peremptory, and lay ſo great weight and ſtreſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it in things of a higher nature, and of a more ſpeculative and curious know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, unleſs he have cultivated his minde with thoſe Sciences and Studies that may inable him the better to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern betwixt truth and errour; which is the greateſt and moſt difficult; though the moſt Noble and Excellent Art in the world; yet in its higheſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and improvement, far from making any man infallible: and though every mans Conſcience, that is, his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgment and opinion, ought and muſt neceſſarily be his Guide; yet ſound judgment will adviſe, that in ſome things we ſhould prefer another mans judgment before our own, eſpecially in matters wherein we have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he hath great skill and knowledge, and better then we our ſelves; as in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59037:43"/>matters of his Calling, whereunto we may be ſtrangers, and never verſed or inſtructed in the things appertaining to it: and therefore a Learned Divine, or the greateſt Scholar, will rather relye upon, and admit of his Taylers judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for cutting out a ſuit of Cloaths, and his Shoo-makers for making him a good pair of Shooes, then preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own; and herein he ceaſeth not ſtill to follow the dictamens of his own private judgment, which he thinks fit, in theſe caſes, with good reaſon, to ſubmit and accommodate to that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Why ſhould not therefore every Mechanick, with the ſame humility, ſubmit to the Opinion of the Learned, in points of Learning; and to their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Scripture, in Scripture-Interpretation; whoſe buſineſs, ſtudy and calling is converſant about, and doth make him a Profeſſor of ſuch knowledge? and if to the Opinion of one, much more to the Opinion of all the moſt Learned and Judicious of a whole Nation, being confirmed and owned by Publick Authority.</p>
               <p>But ſtill if Conſcience cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59037:43"/>to this, you will ſay, Conſcience muſt not be wounded and forced, we muſt not drive, but lead her gently: For if my Conſcience tell me this is a ſin, it is no excuſe before the Judge of Hearts, in committing this which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conceive to be a ſin, to ſay it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by the Commonwealth, a Convocation of Divines, or by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Pariſh, but it appearing to me a ſin, and I ſuppoſing it to be ſuch, in giving way to it condemn my ſelf, and am left inexcuſeable: therefore Conſcience muſt not be violated; and every man will think himſelf obliged to act ſtill according to the dictates and ſuggeſtions of his own Conſcience, let all the Laws of the World, Humane or Divine, ſay what they will: for that hath only the power and influence to work upon a mans Conſcience, which he himſelf conceives to be Law.</p>
               <p>Hence it is manifeſt, that every man in the world that hath any regard to Religion, or a future eſtate, will deſire Liberty of Conſcience; that is, that he may do any thing that in his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgment and Opinion he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59037:44"/>the apteſt means to attain a future Eternal happineſs; and as far as ſuch a future happineſs is to be preferred above temporary tranſitory things, ſo far will he think himſelf obliged by that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Self-love, to prefer the free exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Religion, the means to this happineſs, before life it ſelf, or all the concerns of life. But in the mean time, each man I think will grant, that in reaſon he ought to conſider others as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with himſelf; and that according to the Eternal Laws of Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as he deſires a Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for himſelf, he ought to allow the ſame Liberty of Conſcience to all other men, who for the ſame reaſons, and upon as good grounds as he, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the account of their Eternal Eſtate, think themſelves, and are as much as he alſo, obliged to follow the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their own conſciences or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in order to attain that great propoſed end of Felicity. This being granted, the conſequence thereof muſt of neceſſity be a diſſolution of all Civil Government, where the conſciences of men, as in theſe preſent times, do put
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59037:44"/>them upon ſuch different ways and means of accompliſhing this propoſed end, as are abſolutely inconſiſtent, and cannot be allowed, without interfering and croſſing one another, both in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practiſe.</p>
               <p>But however, if you will have Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience granted to any, then certainly the Supreme Authority of the Nation muſt not be deprived of this Liberty which every private man doth contend for, and thinks of right to belong to himſelf: This cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly were great injuſtice and wrong; yet this being once allowed, there is no more liberty left for any Subject, other then what is conſiſtent with that of the Publick. But you will ſay, the publick Authority ought to take ſuch a courſe, as every man may have his liberty, at leaſt ſo far as is conſiſtent with the Civil Government. I grant it; but then muſt the publick Authority be Judge in this caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> what Liberty may be or is conſiſtent with the Civil Government, and not every private perſon. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſeeing the Supreme Magiſtrate is to have Liberty of Conſcience, which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59037:45"/>I think cannot with reaſon be denied, ſo far as is conſiſtent with the Laws of the Land, and the Religion by them eſtabliſhed. Let us ſuppoſe, as we well may and ought, that he thinks himſelf obliged in Duty and Conſcience, in point of Juſtice and Charity, to take no leſs care for the future, then preſent good eſtate of his people: Hence it will neceſſarily follow, that he ought to uſe all lawful means to ſuppreſs all Religions, Sects and Opinions, which he conceives to be Heretical and Erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and contrary to the National eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed way of Worſhip; and what in him lies, to propagate that which he himſelf conceives to be the true; and unto the obſervance and defence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he is not only by his private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but publick Ingagement obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: For he who ſees another man in his Opinion blinde, and going directly upon a Pit, or Precipice, where he ſhall be ſure to pitch upon his own death, is very much too blame if he do not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from running thus fooliſhly to deſtruction, though the other party ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt him, becauſe he will not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59037:45"/>ſuffer him to go forward upon a certain death: How much more then ſhall he fail, in point of Charity and Duty, who ſeeing men run upon their own Eternal death, by ſlipping into Errours and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, ſhall not indeavour to relieve and recal them, or at leaſt hinder them from drawing the reſt of mankinde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, into the ſame Gulphs of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and perdition, by ſuppreſſing and hindring the growth and propagation of theſe Errours; more eſpecially where bearing the Soveraign Power, that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice lays a duty and obligation upon him, by his particular relation to his Subjects, to be careful of all their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns?</p>
               <p>And hereby it appears, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will ſet up for Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for himſelf, ſeeing he can in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equity do no leſs then allow that liberty to others, as well as deſire it for himſelf, and conſequently to the Soveraign Magiſtrate; this man imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> hereby deprives himſelf of all liberty, more then what the Law of the Land will allow him: for the Conſcience of the Magiſtrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59037:46"/>him to be as careful of the Souls of his Subjects, and their future eſtates, as of their bodies, and their temporal welfare, he can do no leſs, according to Conſcience, then uſe the means and power that is in his hands, according to the Laws of the Land, to ſuppreſs all Religions but the true one; that is, that which he himſelf, as Supreme Head, hath judged ſo to be, by obliging himſelf to defend and conſerve the ſame according to the Laws of the Land. And if you will exclaim againſt him for doing ſo, it is without any reaſon: For having allowed the Propoſition, that every man ought to have Liberty of Conſcience, and by his Conſcience to regulate his actions; you ought not to accuſe him who aſſumes this liberty of acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Conſcience, though it impugnes yours: for to ſay, he acts not according to his Conſcience, or that his Conſcience is erronious or wicked, and therefore not to be a rule to others, is to take upon you, in the firſt caſe, to know that which only God can know, the heart of man; or in the ſecond, to preſume to make your own Conſcience
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59037:46"/>the Standard of Truth, to meaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers by: So that the liberty you contend for, is only a liberty to ſet up, and idolize your own judgment and fancy, above all the world beſides. And hereby it is evident, that Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, other then what is allowed by the National or Civil Power or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, is not a thing to be deſired; or if taken, will certainly diſſolve and bring to ruine all Civil Government; and that man who cannot with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſubmit to the Government in being, whether in a Kingdom, or any other Species of Government, I think his wiſeſt way were to go to ſome ſuch place or Country, where he may freely injoy his own way of worſhip; and if no ſuch can be found, then let him again conſider, what kinde of Religion he hath gotten, that drives him from the ſociety of mankinde: But for every man to think himſelf highly wronged, becauſe he may not be ſuffered to ſet up a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion according to his own fancy or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is to offer the greateſt wrong to all his Fellows, who may with as much Juſtice lay claim to the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59037:47"/>and then will it be impoſſible for any Civil Government to take place or continue, where every man may be allowed the liberty to do what ſeems good in his own eyes, without reſpect to the eſtabliſhed Laws: for who knows, or rather, who knows not, to what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies mens conſciences, or hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical wicked men, under pretence of Conſcience (which is the ſame) are often carried? and therefore Liberty in this kinde is neceſſarily to be reſtrain'd within certain bounds and limits, of which the Supreme Authority ought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> And now having through all theſe ſeveral diſcourſes adhered ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Law of Self-preſervation, or Self-love, perhaps ſome will hence take occaſion to ſay, this ſelfiſh Principle is baſe, and unworthy a Chriſtian, nay even a generous Heathen; our duty to God, and reſpect to the univerſal good of all mankinde, being things to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all ſelf-ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They who have well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what I have ſaid before, will ſave me the trouble of anſwering this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59037:47"/>and be able to do it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. and to the reſt I ſay again, for I have ſaid as much before, Our duty to God, and reſpect to the general good of mankinde, are things inſeparable from our intereſt; there being nothing ſo abſolutely neceſſary to our well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to do our duties to our Creator, and to do good to our Fellow-creatures, which is commanded by the Law of Nature, and by the example of God himſelf; whereby, in imitation of him, in all things to be imitated, and into a ſhadow of whoſe perfections we are to endeavour to form and model our ſelves, as far as our natures are capable of it, we are obliged and injoyned to do good to all; which indeed is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our duties upon the aforeſaid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, but is alſo one of the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and delightful things to all good diſpoſitions, and well-tempered ſpirits, that can be conceived or imagined, and they little better then Devils that are of a contrary ſenſe and judgment. But if you will urge me further, and ſay, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe duties we owe to God and our Neighbours were really diſunited
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59037:48"/>from our intereſt, what were then to be done? I ſay, the very ſuppoſition is wicked, and injurious both to God and man; for it is as much as if we ſhould ſuppoſe God could ceaſe to be, or be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then good, an Attribute and Perfection inſeparable from his Nature: For certainly it could never be judged goodneſs in God, but its contrary, to make our duties to himſelf, and our Neighbours, inconſiſtent with our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, I ſpeak not here of petty worldly ends and advantages, which ſome baſe-minded men account their only intereſt; but that I account our intereſt which is eternally ſo, and upon which our future eſtate and happineſs to all Eternity doth depend; and whatſoever is a means con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to that end, and that only, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our intereſt; and if others will interpoſe it, it is to be at their perils.</p>
               <p>If after all this it be objected ſtill, that if we permit every private man to be Judge of good and evil, juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, right and wrong, and that every man doth and muſt of neceſſity govern himſelf, and direct his actions accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own private judgment and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59037:48"/>conſcience, in order to his well-being; it muſt neceſſarily follow, that many mens private Opinions (as Experience teaches us every day) will make them refractory and diſobedient to the Prince, and may be a cauſe of Rebellion, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and War.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, It hath been ever ſo ſince the World began, and ever will be ſo till all mens private judgments jump in one: Nor is there any remedy for this miſchief, as I conceive, but what I have already mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men to lay aſide pride, prejudice and ſelf-conceit, and be well adviſed before they oppoſe their private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the publick, and the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, which is, that he who hath ſo great, and probably over-weening O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of his own private judgment and conſcience, as to oppoſe them againſt the Publick Authority, he doth it at his own peril, and is obnoxious to the Law; which if he think it more for his true intereſt and happineſs to oppoſe, then ſubmit to, he doth but obſerve the Rule of Self-love, or Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſo doing; and he cannot do
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59037:49"/>otherwiſe (unleſs he could alter his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the means in order to that end) the greateſt ſeeming good being always moſt prevailing with the judgment to determine it: For it is impoſſible for any man to renounce or reſigne the power of determining himſelf what is good and evil, and abſolutely to be therein governed by another mans judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if he act rationally; the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding not being otherwiſe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, but by an apparent good; and where ſeveral apparent goods offer themſelves, the underſtanding muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be ſwayed by that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be the greateſt: and it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any man to make whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever another man pleaſes to call ſo, to ſeem to his reaſon and judgment an apparent good, or the greateſt apparent good; even as much as it is impoſſible for any man to believe black to be white, or white black, pain pleaſure, or pleaſure pain, or that two is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number then three, only becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother man bids him believe them to be ſo: And therefore that we ſhould all believe the Commands of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59037:49"/>to be the only Rule of good and evil, is not only unreaſonable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Humane Society (as hath been ſhewed) but alſo impoſſible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a man could believe what he liſted: yet ſtill ſo long as we all agree that ſuch diſobedience in the Subject to the Civil Magiſtrate, is puniſhable according to the Laws ordained, though private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience put men upon ſuch acts of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the Government may remain firm enough, whilſt every private man ſatisfies the Law, either by active or paſſive obedience, obeying, or ſuffering for his diſobedience: and if the Laws againſt ſuch Diſſenters as cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or tolerated with ſafety in a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government be ſtrictly executed, men will be well adviſed of the grounds upon which they refuſe obedience to Authority, before they thruſt their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers into the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:50"/>
            <head>Books (ſince the fire in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 1666.) printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1673.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Triumphs of Gods Revenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Crying of the Sin of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> With his Miraculous Diſcoveries, and ſevere puniſhments thereof, in 30 ſeveral Tragical Hiſtories, committed in divers Countries beyond the Seas, with Pictures reſembling all the paſſages: Written by <hi>J. Reynolds, Fol.</hi> Printed 1670. price 10 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sylva Sylvarum;</hi> or a Natural Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in ten Centuries: Whereunto is new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly added the Hiſtory of the Prolongati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Life, with the <hi>New Atlantis,</hi> and Articles of inquiry about Metals and Minerals; by <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam.</hi> To which is added the Authors Life; by Dr. <hi>Rawley,</hi> in <hi>Fol.</hi> Printed 1670. price 8 s.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59037:50"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Jeſuites Morals;</hi> collected by a Doctor of the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> who hath faithfully extracted them out of the Jeſuites own Books: Tranſlated out of French, in <hi>Fol.</hi> Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1670. price 10 s.</item>
               <item>A Geographical Deſcription of the World, in four parts, illuſtrated with Maps: Writ in French by <hi>Monſieur Sanſon,</hi> Geographer to the French King, and Engliſhed and augmented by <hi>R. B.</hi> Gent. in <hi>Fol.</hi> Printed 1670. price 20 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Kempis</hi> Chriſtian Pattern, in twenty fours, price 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drexelius</hi> Conſiderations on Eternity in Engliſh, in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> Catechiſme, <hi>Greek, Latine</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with a <hi>Praxis</hi> to it; by. <hi>Chr. Waſe, F. Goldſmith,</hi> Eſquire, <hi>B. Beale, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clark's <hi>Praxis Curiae Admiralitatis,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> Tract of Schiſm, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hammond's</hi> Compleat Meaſurer, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Life of <hi>Renatus Des Cartes,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59037:51"/>
               <item>Enigmatical Characters, by <hi>R. F.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi> Price 1 s.</item>
               <item>Three papers preſented to the Royal Society by <hi>Tho. Hobbes</hi> againſt Doctor <hi>Wallis.</hi> Printed 1671. price 6 d.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ynwaring</hi> of health and long life, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Compleat Phyſitian qualified and dignified, ſhewing the riſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of Phyſick, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nomenclatura,</hi> Greek, Latine and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, for the uſe of Schools, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hodder</hi>'s Vulgar Arithmetick, in 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gerhard</hi>'s Meditations in Latin, in 12</item>
               <item>An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Ferguſons</hi> Book, intituled, <hi>Juſtification only upon Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction:</hi> Wherein he is friendly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, fully ſilenc'd, and clearly inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Whereunto is added a Diſcourſe of the extent of Chriſts Paſſion and Death, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> Printed 1670 price 1 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hobbes De Principiis &amp; Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione Geometricum,</hi> in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Blunts</hi> Voyage into the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant:</hi> Being a brief Relation of a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lately performed from <hi>England,</hi> by the way of <hi>Venice,</hi> into <hi>Dalmatia, Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia, Boſna, Hungary, Macedonia, Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaly,
<pb facs="tcp:59037:51"/>Thrace, Rhodes</hi> and <hi>Eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt,</hi> unto <hi>Grand Cairo:</hi> With particular obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning the Modern condition of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and other people under that Empire, in 12. Price 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Compleat Vineyard:</hi> Or an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way for the planting of Vines ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the German and French manner, and long practiſed in <hi>England:</hi> Wherein is ſet forth the ways, and all the circumſtances neceſſary for the planting a Vineyard, with the Election of the Soil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo the faſhion of Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes, the manner of bruiſing and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Grapes, and how to advance our Engliſh Wines, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> Enlarged by the Author. Printed 1670. price 1 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached at the Funeral of a ſober Religious man found drowned in a Pit; wherein Sudden Death is moſt excellently handled, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> Printed 1670. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>The Deaf and Dumb Mans diſcourſe; or a Treatiſe concerning thoſe that are born Deaf and Dumb; containing a Diſcovery of their Underſtanding, and the Methods they uſe to manifeſt the ſentiments of their minds. Together
<pb facs="tcp:59037:52"/>with an additional Tract of the reaſon and ſpeech of Inanimate Creatures; by <hi>Geo. Sibſcota.</hi> Printed 1670. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>A Deſcription of <hi>Candia</hi> in its Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Modern State; with an account of the Siege begun by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, 1666. Continued 1667, 1668, and ſurrendred 1669. With all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſages, and the Articles of Surrender. Printed 1669 in <hi>Octavo,</hi> price 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Court of Curioſity:</hi> Wherein by the <hi>Algebra</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> the moſt intricate Queſtions are reſolved, and Dreams and Viſions explained and interpreted: ſo which is added <hi>A Treatiſe of Phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> publiſhed in <hi>French;</hi> and for the excellency of it, tranſlated into <hi>Dutch, Spaniſh, Italian, &amp;c.</hi> and now out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The ſecond Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cleared from many miſtakes of the former Impreſſion, both in the <hi>Fortune-Book</hi> and <hi>Dreams:</hi> With an Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Table added; ſo that now the Dreams, or Anſwers to Queſtions, may with eaſe be ſound out, in 12. Printed 1672. price 2 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Flower-Garden:</hi> Briefly ſhewing
<pb facs="tcp:59037:52"/>how moſt Flowers are to be ordered; the time of flowring, taking them up, and planting them again; and how they are increaſed by Layers of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, Slips, Cuttings, Seeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with other obſervations relating to a <hi>Flower-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> Whereunto is added the <hi>Gardiners Dialling, viz.</hi> How to make an exact Horizontal Dial on a Graſs-plat, the knot of a Garden, or elſewhere; by <hi>W. Hughes,</hi> in 12. Printed 1672. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Memoires</hi> of the Life and rare unheard-of Adventures of <hi>Henrietta Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liere;</hi> being the Remarks of the ſtrange and Heroick actions of a great Lady in <hi>France</hi> now living. Written by her ſelf in <hi>French,</hi> and tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in 12. Printed 1672. price 2 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The American Phyſitian;</hi> or, <hi>A Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Roots, Plants, Trees, Shrubs, Fruits, Herbs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>growing in the Engliſh Plantations in America:</hi> Deſcribing the place, time, names, kinds, temperature, vertues and uſes of them, either for Diet or Phyſick: with the Governour of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica's</hi> Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereunto is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the ways of making <hi>Chocoletta,</hi> and its vertues; by <hi>W. H.</hi> in 12. Printed 1672. price 1 s.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59037:53"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lux Mathematica:</hi> Wherein the 20 years Controverſie in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> betwixt Dr. <hi>Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> is debated, and dedicated to the <hi>Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;</hi> by <hi>R.R.</hi> in <hi>Quarto.</hi> Printed 1672. price 5 s.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Poetry <hi>and</hi> Plays.</head>
               <item>Epigrams, of all ſorts, made at divers times on ſeveral occaſions, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> Printed 1670. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>Poems written by the Right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>Richard Corbet,</hi> late Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi> The third Edition corrected and inlarged. Printed 1672 in 12. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vittoria Corombona,</hi> or the <hi>White De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil:</hi> A Tragedy, as it is often acted at the <hi>Theatre Royal,</hi> by their Majeſties Servants, in <hi>Quarto.</hi> Printed 1672. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Old Troop,</hi> or <hi>Monſieur Raggou;</hi> A Comedy, as it was acted at the <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre Royal.</hi> Written by <hi>John Lacy,</hi> in <hi>Quarto.</hi> Printed 1672. price 1 s.</item>
               <item>The Travels of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> as they were by himſelf related, in <hi>Homer</hi>'s ninth, tenth, eleventh and twelfth Books of his <hi>Odyſſes</hi> to the King of <hi>Phaeacia.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:59037:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
